<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Frivolous Musings</title>
    <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Frivolous Musings</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-za</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://lordgrenville.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Populism</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/populism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/populism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Populism is hard to define. It can be associated with both the political left and right, and, although it doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound like a pejorative term (what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with being popular?), it&amp;rsquo;s one of those terms people only used to describe others (negatively). I used to think of it as meaning &amp;ldquo;anti-elitist&amp;rdquo;, or basically something which is popular but most educated people think is stupid. But I&amp;rsquo;ve come up with something a bit clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;democracy&amp;rdquo; can mean two somewhat contradictory things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the will of the majority&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a system of checks and balances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So ignoring the will of the people is certainly anti-democratic, but following them too freely, without letting other aspects of government put the brakes on it, is also a bad outcome. This is Plato&amp;rsquo;s critique of democracy in the &lt;em&gt;Republic&lt;/em&gt;, and also why the authors of the &lt;em&gt;Federalist Papers&lt;/em&gt; reject democracy in favour of &amp;ldquo;republicanism&amp;rdquo;. But when people use the term today they refer more or less to &amp;ldquo;representative&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;liberal&amp;rdquo; democracy, which attempts to mitigate these critiques in two ways: by weakening centralised power and distributing more of it to individuals, and by adding institutional roadblocks which slow down hasty decision making and encourage broader consensus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the contradiction. As an example, imagine Ruritania has elected a new president by a small but clear majority. His first act in power is to outlaw the main opposition newspaper. The Ruritanian high court tries to block this, on the basis of a general precedent allowing free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foreign media outlets accuse the Ruritanian president of &amp;ldquo;assaulting democracy&amp;rdquo; by trying to restrict free speech, which we associate with the kind of liberal environment necessary for true democracy. However, the president&amp;rsquo;s supporters argue that &lt;em&gt;they,&lt;/em&gt; in fact, are standing up for democracy, since the will of the majority of the people is to ban this newspaper, while some latte-sipping, unelected, out-of-touch eggheads from the high court are trying to obstruct them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of conflict plays out all the time, and while this example is a clear case of liberal left vs populist right, it can easily go both ways. To take a real life example, the United States has a majority of &amp;ldquo;liberal&amp;rdquo; voters (Republicans have won the popular vote in a presidential election only once in the last thirty years), and so major areas of conflict - voter registration laws, the structure of the Senate/Electoral College/Supreme Court - tend to be expressed in terms of liberals (Democrats) arguing for the majority to be heard, and Republicans arguing for the importance of the other aspects of democracy, such as checks and balances, maintaining precedents, constitutionality, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to a slightly more charitable definition of populism: that there is an inherent tension in the two contradictory definitions of democracy, and that the ideal is probably a dynamic synthesis that changes over time, honouring institutional checks and balances while also being attentive to the voice of the people; and that &amp;ldquo;populism&amp;rdquo; is our term for someone who leans too far towards the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Corruption</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was listening to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://newbooksnetwork.com/epstein&#34;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; (about metaphysics in the social sciences, very interesting but not the topic of this post) and the guest mentioned as an aside the principal-agent theory of political corruption, pretty common in economically-inclined poli-sci literature.&lt;label for=&#34;sidenote-e594f12148fa9415207f539ecf993860-0&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle sidenote-number&#34;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;sidenote-e594f12148fa9415207f539ecf993860-0&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;/&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;sidenote&#34;&gt;Susan Rose-Ackerman, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/book/9780125963503/corruption&#34;&gt;Corruption: A Study in Political Economy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; seems to be the classic&lt;/span&gt;
The idea that politicians will rationally try to maximise personal gain unless held accountable by voters struck me as excessively cynical. Aren&amp;rsquo;t they at least somewhat motivated by a desire to serve the public, shame about very explicit graft, a basic sense of right and wrong? Somewhat serendipitously I came across a couple of counterexamples later the same day which disabused me of my innocence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Israel, income from residential rentals is tax-exempt up to a certain threshold, and has a reduced flat rate for any amount above that. This unusual rule - which doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to exist in other countries, and has obvious distorting effects on the (already heated) housing market - doesn&amp;rsquo;t make much sense. One common reason offered for it is that many of the legislators themselves own rental properties. I can&amp;rsquo;t assess the truth of this, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.globes.co.il/news/article.aspx?did=1000967993&#34;&gt;here it is&lt;/a&gt; from a law professor: &amp;ldquo;The usual explanation given for this loophole is &amp;lsquo;guess how many legislators benefit from it&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Not about a politician, but still relevant.) The former head of the Diabetes Association(!) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RonnyLinder/status/1468157746994417671&#34;&gt;appeared today in Parliament&lt;/a&gt; as a paid lobbyist for Coca-Cola to argue against a tax on diet soda. He denied being paid until he was asked about it several times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Gelman had a &lt;a href=&#34;https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2021/12/03/46112/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; the other day about Harry Truman lying about his poverty, and researchers in general who take money to represent dubious causes. He suggested that the motivation is often not financial but psychological: pride at being offered money to consult, or some idea of how the recipient will use the money for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money blinds, is I guess the point. Excuses will always be found if the payoff is big enough.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scraping Kevin Lewis</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/kevin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/kevin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kevin Lewis&#39; daily &lt;em&gt;Findings&lt;/em&gt; blog at National Affairs is a great way to stay on top of social science news, presenting a daily themed collection of abstracts of recent papers. The site is free to read, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer an RSS feed, which is my preferred way to consume it. I decided to write a short Python script to scrape new posts into a local XML file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic script I started with went to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalaffairs.com/authors/detail/kevin-lewis&#34;&gt;the author&amp;rsquo;s page&lt;/a&gt;, found the box with most recent posts, followed and scraped each link, encoded them as RSS (basically URL-encoding the HTML tags), added opening and closing RSS XML tags, and saved the file. In further iterations I added the ability to open the file if it exists, check if an item exists (and not scrape it), and cleaned up the code. Once I was happy with it, the last thing I wanted to add (for now!) was the ability to run it on the reg. The code is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lordgrenville/scrape_kevin&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first instinct was to run &lt;code&gt;crontab -e&lt;/code&gt; and set up a weekly run there. But I found that since my Macbook goes to sleep quite aggressively to save power, often the job wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be carried out. Turns out that macOS has a built in tool called &lt;code&gt;launchd&lt;/code&gt; which is recommended over cron, and can also run after waking if it missed its cue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add it I created a file called &lt;code&gt;~/Library/LaunchAgents/update_lewis.plist&lt;/code&gt;, with the command arguments as outlined &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.launchd.info/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Then I called &lt;code&gt;launchctl load ~/Library/LaunchAgents/update_lewis.plist&lt;/code&gt; (cancel with &lt;code&gt;unload&lt;/code&gt;), and voilà!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes from Installing Arch Linux</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/arch/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/arch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About six months ago I downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://archlinux.org/download/&#34;&gt;the Arch ISO&lt;/a&gt; and stuck it on a thumb drive. I finally got around to installing it now - I was nervous about accidentally nuking my computer, so didn&amp;rsquo;t want to try dual-boot the way I would with a distro with a graphical installer, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yuk7/ArchWSL&#34;&gt;running it via WSL&lt;/a&gt; would be missing the point. I finally got my hands on an old laptop I could mess around with and did it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, it was pretty simple following the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Installation_guide&#34;&gt;installation guide from the Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. The only hairy bit was editing my disk partitions via &lt;code&gt;fdisk&lt;/code&gt; - I relied on &lt;a href=&#34;https://itsfoss.com/install-arch-linux/&#34;&gt;this guide&lt;/a&gt; at that point. But there were two notable issues which held me up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first was expired PGP keys. I ran into a lot of &lt;code&gt;Key could not be verified locally&lt;/code&gt; messages while installing, and one page told me to update my keyring with &lt;code&gt;pacman -Su archlinux-keyring&lt;/code&gt;. This resulted in trying to install a lot more software and running out of space in my thumb drive. I also tried deleting everything in &lt;code&gt;/etc/pacman.d/gnupg&lt;/code&gt; and rerunning &lt;code&gt;pacman-key --init &amp;amp;&amp;amp; pacman-key --populate archlinux&lt;/code&gt;, all to no avail. Eventually I just downloaded the newest version, overwrote it onto my thumb drive, and began from scratch. This time it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other major issue I had was with BIOS vs UEFI. It seemed like my machine was using the legacy BIOS boot, since there was no directory called &lt;code&gt;/sys/firmware/efi&lt;/code&gt;. Based on this I initially created just one partition, &lt;code&gt;/dev/sda&lt;/code&gt;, on which I mounted root based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://itsfoss.com/install-arch-linux/&#34;&gt;the above-mentioned guide&lt;/a&gt;. After installing and rebooting, I got stuck in a boot loop where the machine was turning to the router and asking for a DHCP lease&amp;hellip;apparently skipping past the HDD boot medium and trying to boot from the network! That is, it didn&amp;rsquo;t recognise that there was an OS installed. I once again started over (the installation process is pretty quick, so this isn&amp;rsquo;t such a big deal) and redid it while adding &lt;code&gt;/dev/sda1&lt;/code&gt; for UEFI and &lt;code&gt;/dev/sda2&lt;/code&gt; for root. This time it worked smoothly, so apparently I did need the ESP partition?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final note: Arch doesn&amp;rsquo;t include sudo with its basic install, so you can just grab it with pacman. But note that if you first created a non-root user, you get a &amp;ldquo;naughty, naughty&amp;rdquo; message when trying to use sudo as no-root. I had to set a default &lt;code&gt;\$EDITOR&lt;/code&gt;, and then call &lt;code&gt;visudo&lt;/code&gt; and add myself to sudo-capable users. Once I had this I installed &lt;code&gt;yay&lt;/code&gt;, Firefox, and vim and called it a day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Complete Idiot&#39;s Guide to Doom Emacs</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/emacs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(This guide assumes familiarity with Vim, git and command line, but no prior knowledge of Emacs. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jesshamrick.com/2012/09/10/absolute-beginners-guide-to-emacs/&#34;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is a good guide from zero to Emacs. I was also helped/inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://noelwelsh.com/posts/2019-01-10-doom-emacs.html&#34;&gt;Noel Welsh&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; Doom guide, and that of mad genius &lt;a href=&#34;https://tecosaur.github.io/emacs-config/config.html&#34;&gt;Tecosaur&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After several aborted attempts to get started with Emacs, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally made some sense of it. Since there aren&amp;rsquo;t many basic guides online, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d document my process. Vim (which I&amp;rsquo;m using to type this) is a lot simpler to get started with (as soon as you figure out how to quit&amp;hellip;) I think that has to do with its greater simplicity, as well as the fact that there&amp;rsquo;s basically only one flavour. (NeoVim is from a user&amp;rsquo;s perspective mostly identical, and if you&amp;rsquo;re using &lt;code&gt;vi&lt;/code&gt; you probably know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing.) Emacs by contrast is a whole world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first question I had to deal with is: which Emacs do I use? Vanilla Emacs looks like something from the Stone Age, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer you enough out of the box to persuade you to learn it - at least that was my experience. I was tempted back first with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spacemacs.org/&#34;&gt;Spacemacs&lt;/a&gt;, and finally settled on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hlissner/doom-emacs&#34;&gt;Doom Emacs&lt;/a&gt;, which will be the subject of this guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To clarify, all of these involve installing Emacs, and then building stuff on top of it. Emacs adds a &lt;code&gt;.emacs.d&lt;/code&gt; folder to your home directory for your personal config, and these both customize that to look snazzier and use some extra tools right out of the box. Both Spacemacs and Doom emphasise &lt;code&gt;Evil&lt;/code&gt;, an Emacs layer allowing Vim keys to be used instead of learning Emacs keys (though they allow either to be configured). Doom also stresses quick loading time and simplicity: it strives to do some basic config and let you get on with your work, rather than going down the rabbit-hole of eternal tweaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After installing Emacs and cloning the Doom repo, you will have a &lt;code&gt;.doom.d&lt;/code&gt; folder alongside &lt;code&gt;emacs.d&lt;/code&gt;. This is where you will do everything. &lt;code&gt;.doom.d&lt;/code&gt; contains three files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;config.el&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;packages.el&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;/code&gt; is where you select what you want Doom to take care of. This part is the most abstracted away from regular Emacs. Instead of installing, say, a package for Python development, you tell Doom you want to use Python and it will install the Python stuff it recommends.  If you want to know how to configure this, you need to look inside the repo itself: &lt;code&gt;~/doom-emacs/modules/lang/python/README.org&lt;/code&gt; in this example. (Don&amp;rsquo;t make changes here, though, unless you want to contribute to Doom development, in which case you&amp;rsquo;re way beyond this humble guide.) That README will tell you what packages are used, and sometimes which flags you can add. For example, you can add a &lt;code&gt;conda&lt;/code&gt; flag in Python by replacing &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;(python +conda)&lt;/code&gt;. The more languages and other tools you add, the slower start-up will be, so take only what you need. You can edit it at any time, but you must then sync, either with &lt;code&gt;~/.emacs.d/bin/doom sync&lt;/code&gt;, or if you have Emacs open with &lt;code&gt;M-x doom-reload&lt;/code&gt;. (&lt;code&gt;M-x&lt;/code&gt; is META-x, or alt-x, the Emacs key for a menu for typing in commands. In Evil this is &lt;code&gt;SPC :&lt;/code&gt; However this stuff is found in many newbie guides, so I&amp;rsquo;ll try focus on stuff that I struggled to find online.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason you have to sync after changing &lt;code&gt;init.el&lt;/code&gt; is that it relies on Doom doing some work behind the scenes to install and load
packages - those are the abstractions. &lt;code&gt;config.el&lt;/code&gt;, by contrast, is a regular Emacs lisp document, so any changes you make in it can be
evaluated and applied immediately. &lt;code&gt;config.el&lt;/code&gt; is where you&amp;rsquo;ll make any custom changes you want. &lt;em&gt;Whenever people tell you online to add
stuff with&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;(setq blah blah)&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;you should put it in here.&lt;/em&gt; If you want to install any &lt;em&gt;packages&lt;/em&gt;, which in Emacs are usually installed from
a repository called MELPA, but can also come from the web (eg GitHub), you put them in &lt;code&gt;packages.el&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default Emacs uses different workspaces, each one containing a project. When you start working you should add your project root, and then you can navigate within it with &lt;code&gt;SPC f f&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, a word about modes. Continuing the musical analogy of chords (key combinations), Emacs has modes which are basically added functionality within a buffer. A major mode is usually the language type, and a buffer can only have one, while it can have many minor modes. Major mode chords in Evil begin with &lt;code&gt;SPC m&lt;/code&gt;, after which you will see a guide in the minibuffer with your next options. (Always true in Doom.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this should be enough to get you started with a project, the correct major mode, and some nice looking defaults. I definitely haven&amp;rsquo;t been persuaded to drop Vim as my default &lt;code&gt;$EDITOR&lt;/code&gt;, but I see it as my day-to-day tool, with Emacs as more of a speciality tool with capabilities like &lt;a href=&#34;https://magit.vc/&#34;&gt;Magit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;code&gt;org-mode&lt;/code&gt;, and way more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status &amp; Jewish Intellectuals</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/status/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/status/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently asked a French friend why that country produces so many brilliant mathematicians and scientists - not really expecting a good answer. He replied that in France, being an academic or theoretician is seen as the most admirable position to aspire to, on a par with philosopher or artist. However, engineers and entrepreneurs are associated with far less prestige, which would roughly explain why so many of those scientists and mathematicians end up working for foreign companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It reminded me that when I was growing up, I thought of writers, historians, philosophers and other intellectuals as most worthy of respect, and assumed that I should want to do something similar when I was older, if I could afford it. It is possible that this is undergoing a sea-change, as the increased prominence of information technology and financial difficulties of media and academia increase the social capital (in Bourdieu&amp;rsquo;s term) associated with &amp;ldquo;STEM&amp;rdquo; subjects. Nonetheless, I was surprised to find a very bald expression of this idea in Stefan Zweig&amp;rsquo;s memoir &lt;em&gt;The World of Yesterday&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is generally assumed that getting rich is a Jew’s true and typical aim in life. Nothing could be further from the truth. Getting rich, to a Jew, is only an interim stage, a means to his real end, by no means his aim in itself. The true desire of a Jew, his inbuilt ideal, is to rise to a higher social plane by becoming an intellectual. Even the most prosperous Jew would rather marry his daughter to an indigent intellectual than a merchant. This high regard for intellectuals runs through all classes of Jewish society, and the poorest pedlar who carries his pack through wind and weather will try to give at least one son the chance of studying at university, however great the sacrifices he must make, and will consider it an honour to the entire family that one of them is clearly regarded as an intellectual: a professor, a scholar, a musician. It is as if such a man’s achievements ennobled them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another expression of this I found in Tom Wolfe&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.esquire.com/news-politics/a12149389/robert-noyce-tom-wolfe/&#34;&gt;long, interesting &lt;em&gt;Esquire&lt;/em&gt; history&lt;/a&gt; of Bob Noyce (co-founder of Fairchild Semiconductor and Intel), discussing why so many early tech pioneers came from the Midwest and West Coast, rather than the traditional East Coast centres of intellectual brilliance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back east engineering was an unfashionable field. The East looked to Europe in matters of intellectual fashion, and in Europe the ancient aristocratic bias against manual labor lived on. Engineering was looked upon as nothing more than manual labor raised to the level of a science. There was &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo; science and there was engineering, which was merely practical. Back east engineers ranked, socially, below lawyers; doctors; Army colonels; Navy captains; English, history, biology, chemistry, and physics professors; and business executives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Douglas Adams Principle</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/adams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/adams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a great quote from Douglas Adams&#39; posthumous final novel, &lt;em&gt;The Salmon of Doubt&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything that is in the world when you’re born is normal and ordinary and is just a natural part of the way the world works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything that&amp;rsquo;s invented between when you’re fifteen and thirty-five is new and exciting and revolutionary and you can probably get a career in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything invented after you&amp;rsquo;re thirty-five is against the natural order of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is applicable to a lot of things - politics, say. There&amp;rsquo;s a common stereotype that people become more conservative as they age. Logically we could see most people becoming more politically aware in their late teens/twenties, and then seeing those new politics as the way forward. As they become older, newer innovations just seem wrong. I think I recall Paul Krugman saying on a podcast that older members of the Federal Reserve are more opposed to keeping interest rates low, because they remember the high interest rates of the &amp;rsquo;70s. Younger members, who have never experienced high inflation, are more concerned about the labour market and willing to consider low rates in the longer term. Even though this seems like a simple, easily noticed cognitive bias, it can be hard to countermand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a more prosaic sense, I find as I get older that I am less and less interested in discovering new music. It isn&amp;rsquo;t that I think new music is less good; I just &lt;em&gt;know enough&lt;/em&gt; music! And likewise, to a lesser extent, with TV and movies: I have enough to get by, I don&amp;rsquo;t need any more. Of course one could make an effort to overcome this, by constantly exposing oneself to new stuff, it just takes work - there are plenty of people who keep up with new gadgets or music well into old age. But it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem worth it to most people. Perhaps in the political sphere the effort is more worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gifts</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/gifts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/gifts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently read the book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/160171.Just_for_Fun&#34;&gt;Just for Fun&lt;/a&gt;, a lot of which focuses on Linus Torvalds&#39; battle for his operating system, Linux, to be &amp;ldquo;Open Source&amp;rdquo; software. Open Source doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean free; but it  means that the software&amp;rsquo;s code (the source) is freely available, so anyone can copy it. Thus there&amp;rsquo;s no viable business in selling the code, but there could be in supplying and installing the software for less tech-savvy users, or in ancillary services such as support. At the time, the &lt;em&gt;bête noire&lt;/em&gt; of OS was Bill Gates, who made a reasonable argument: OS software made it hard to earn a living from software, meaning worse quality for everybody. Yet today OS has basically won out, with even Microsoft embracing Linux and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/microsoft?q=license%3Agpl-3.0+license%3Amit&amp;amp;type=&amp;amp;language=&#34;&gt;open-sourcing&lt;/a&gt; hundreds of projects. So how does the Open Source world square the circle of making it pay?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of something the financial writer Matt Levine says about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2017-05-02/litvaking-and-lending&#34;&gt;gift economy&lt;/a&gt; (based on the essay &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Gift_(essay)&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Gift&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by the anthropologist Marcel Mauss). At a basic level, people trade goods based on pure financial value; but at a very large scale - say, an oil-and-gas company is looking for bankers to facilitate an acquisition - decisions are made much more based on gifts and relationships, which are not anchored in pure economic rationality. For example, the bank may gift the company&amp;rsquo;s decision-makers watches or fancy dinners or golfing weekends, in the hope that at some later point, they will remember them for some major deal (never as an explicit &lt;em&gt;quid pro quo&lt;/em&gt;, which would seem distatestful to both sides).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways the software world has moved toward this model. Companies want to hire star developers, and to do so try to impress them with their friendliness toward open-source, perhaps through sponsorships or by allowing some of their employees to contribute to open-source projects on company time. They may also open up some of their own source code, usually from side projects which aren&amp;rsquo;t part of their main business model, or as a way to tempt customers to integrate into their ecosystem. On the developer side, a beginner programmer may contribute to an open-source project related to her specialty as a way of making an name for herself. In each case, these are not transactions based on economic value, but part of a more sophisticated ritual in which each side hopes to gain, but is able to talk in terms of lofty values such as the good of the community, gift-giving, and generally a world free of grubby pecuniary thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/wesmckinn/status/1237488666425131011&#34;&gt;this complaint&lt;/a&gt; (representative of many others) shows, in practice the model doesn&amp;rsquo;t  work as well as we might hope.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pragmatism</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/pragmatism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/pragmatism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Will to Believe&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Is Life Worth Living?&lt;/em&gt;, IV), William James writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose, for instance, that you are climbing a mountain, and have worked yourself into a position from which the only escape is by a terrible leap. Have faith that you can successfully make it, and your feet are nerved to its accomplishment. But mistrust yourself, and think of all the sweet things you have heard the scientists say of maybes, and you will hesitate so long that, at last, all unstrung and trembling, and launching yourself in a moment of despair, you roll in the abyss. In such a case (and it belongs to an enormous class), the part of wisdom as well as of courage is to believe what is in the line of your needs, for only by such belief is the need fulfilled. Refuse to believe, and you shall indeed be right, for you shall irretrievably perish. But believe, and again you shall be right, for you shall save yourself. You make one or the other of two possible universes true by your trust or mistrust,—both universes having been only maybes, in this particular, before you contributed your act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve come across a similar idea in &lt;a href=&#34;https://philosophybites.com/2014/03/david-papineau-on-philosophy-and-sport.html&#34;&gt;this podcast&lt;/a&gt;: that &lt;em&gt;the fact of believing in something&lt;/em&gt; makes it more likely to happen. This can be true in mountaineering (James&#39; example), sport (as in the podcast), or in business, which I&amp;rsquo;ve always thought takes extraordinary self-belief: most businesses fail, so one has to wilfully ignore the laws of probability in order to start a new one, yet countless people do, and society benefits from their appetite for risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who tends towards &amp;ldquo;rationalism&amp;rdquo; (using the term colloquially), I struggle to understand this impulse. How does one ignore reality and leap ahead into something, convincing oneself that is true? And, at what point should reality be allowed to once again influence one&amp;rsquo;s decision-making? The perenially loss-making business foolhardily propelled into an avalanche of red ink comes to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lordgrenville.github.io/img/wework.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Look before you leap?&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also relevant in what we might might call &amp;ldquo;self-help&amp;rdquo;. Common advice goes that one should &amp;ldquo;be oneself&amp;rdquo; and not worry about what other people think. And sure, confidence is attractive. But judgements from others are also a way in which society communicates; obviously one doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to entirely cut oneself off from what others think. Say someone has an intensely annoying laugh, something which causes anyone with normal hearing deep psychic pain - wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be more reasonable for him to try change it, rather than soldier on believing that others should just accept him?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But maybe I&amp;rsquo;m too rational to understand all this&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tar Hack</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/tar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/tar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a funny &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/1168/&#34;&gt;xkcd cartoon&lt;/a&gt; about the &lt;code&gt;tar&lt;/code&gt; command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/tar_2x.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does one remember those ridiculous single letter commands? My preferred solution is to first consult with &lt;a href=&#34;https://tldr.sh/&#34;&gt;TLDR&lt;/a&gt;, but Justin Abrahams has a fun solution &lt;a href=&#34;https://justin.abrah.ms/bash/forgotten_friend_3.html&#34;&gt;over at his blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;  extract &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; -f &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; in
        *.tar.bz2&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;        tar xjf &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.tar.gz&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;         tar xzf &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.bz2&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;            bunzip2 &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.rar&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;            unrar x &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.gz&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;             gunzip &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;         &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.tar&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;            tar xf &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;         &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.tbz2&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;           tar xjf &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.tgz&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;            tar xzf &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;        &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.zip&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;            unzip &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *.Z&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;              uncompress &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
        *&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;                &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#39;1&amp;#39; cannot be extracted via extract()&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;esac&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#39;1&amp;#39; is not a valid file&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Appended, naturally, to &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communication</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/communication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve just finished a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/560818.Speaking_Peace&#34;&gt;book on Nonviolent Comunication&lt;/a&gt; and thought it would have made a good pairing with one I read last year, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26156469-never-split-the-difference&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Never Split the Difference&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as a lesson in effective communication. The latter is about getting what you want from your counterparty, no matter your relationship afterwards. An adversarial, zero-sum situation is assumed, and Voss (the author, a former FBI hostage negotiator) urges the reader to push for everything, using empathy toward the counterparty only as a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, Rosenberg urges something of the opposite approach: creating a peaceful relationship even at the risk of not achieving your goals. He has a somewhat Buddhistic approach to life, seeing all people as essentially good and the goal of communication as seeing the goodness in the counterparty, validating their feelings without criticising (this applies equally to oneself), and trying to find a way in which everyone’s goals can be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both authors present a bevy of case studies in which they used their principles to achieve miraculous results, even in cases which seemed like certain exceptions. I think that both authors imply a falsehood, without making it explicit: &lt;em&gt;my principles will work in all situations&lt;/em&gt;. When push comes to shove, both would have to admit that some situations are simply insoluble; no amount of negotiating savvy or peace-building communication will lead to a positive outcome. Nonetheless, such cases are rare, and some hyperbole is probably needed in order to convince sceptical readers to apply these rules among their families and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boredom</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/boredom/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/boredom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I almost always have earphones in, filling up the time in which I&amp;rsquo;m not actively focusing on something else with a steady patter of podcasts or mildly interesting books. But occasionally I wonder: aren&amp;rsquo;t I missing out on being alone with my thoughts, the serendipitous free flow borne of tedium? Maybe it isn&amp;rsquo;t worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have a control: one day a week, I forswear all electronic devices, and when I go for walks it&amp;rsquo;s just me and my own thoughts. I guess the ideal would be for me to ponder hard problems, or come up with a more efficient solution to a maths problem (this actually did happen the other day, for &lt;a href=&#34;https://projecteuler.net/problem=205&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;! But most of the time the topics seem to be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inventing the perfect response for situations where I didn&amp;rsquo;t have one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting angry about the news&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagining situations where someone tries to beat me up, but then it turns out that I have superpowers and I beat &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; up (is this normal for an adult??? What does this say about me!?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tentative conclusion: I&amp;rsquo;m not missing out on much. Although it&amp;rsquo;s possible that the &amp;ldquo;boredom premium&amp;rdquo; is cumulative, and only after building up a long period of boredom does true creativity flourish. By cycling between long periods of hyperstimulation and brief pauses, I&amp;rsquo;m just letting my overstimulated mind lapse into white noise on its off days. ¯_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally Figured Out Monty Hall!</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/monty_hall/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/monty_hall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DeegC/monty_hall_paradox&#34;&gt;this explanation&lt;/a&gt; (coding it out in Ruby made it clearer to me, but it&amp;rsquo;s really the verbal explanation that worked).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the outset you have doors A, B and C. Given the choice between A or B and C, obviously you would take the latter. That&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re choosing here! B and C, which combined have a greater chance of being correct. It&amp;rsquo;s more likely that it was in the two you didn&amp;rsquo;t choose: specifically the one of them which isn&amp;rsquo;t wrong. But they still represent 2/3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=22717754&#34;&gt;HN commenter&lt;/a&gt; put it, it&amp;rsquo;s easier to think of it when it&amp;rsquo;s 100 doors. To begin, you choose one. What&amp;rsquo;s the chance you&amp;rsquo;re correct? A measly 1%. You almost certainly got it wrong. Imagine if you could switch to select &lt;em&gt;the other 99&lt;/em&gt;. Of course you&amp;rsquo;d do it! Now the host opens the 98 goat doors. The other 99 are 98 goats + 1 &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt;. Of course you should switch! &lt;em&gt;You picked the minority, so the majority of times you are wrong. You&amp;rsquo;re being given a chance to switch to the majority&lt;/em&gt;. Of course, if no door is opened, you&amp;rsquo;re still picking one of 3 - you&amp;rsquo;re still a minority, so it makes no difference if you switch or stay.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Twitter Works in 2019</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/twitter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Someone tweets: I like mushrooms. Mushrooms are great. Yummy! Hits “send tweet”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the replies are from the person’s followers. “Wow, you’re so  right! You have the best take on mushrooms.” “Totally! Mushrooms rule!”  “Ugh people who don’t like mushrooms be like [GIF from The Office]”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then one person says “mushrooms are OK, but garlic is also cool”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone else goes: “oh look it’s reply guy! here to mansplain the evils of mushrooms. Who hurt you?!?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kind of understand the product decision behind this, because in  previous iterations of Twitter, what would happen is some random user  with a Nazi avatar searching the hashtag #mushrooms would find the tweet and say something like “death to the mushroom eaters!!! I will track  you down and rape and kill you. I know where you live” So helpfully,  Twitter wanted to make the conversation more like a conversation in a  safe space between friends, and less like an open space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is just that Twitter is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; an open space: lots of people (like me) follow influential people because we want to hear  their views, but it’s nice to see those views encounter the views of  others who disagree, fostering conversation. When someone’s conversation is only with their acolytes, the public discourse is impoverished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a good solution for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This essay is indebted to Megan McArdle’s idea &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.econtalk.org/megan-mcardle-on-internet-shaming-and-online-mobs/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; about friend circles and internet circles.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carrying Podcasts From the Well On My Shoulders, Like In the Old Days</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/podcasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/podcasts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In general my view on podcasts is the shorter the better. So I really
like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/podcasts/view&#34;&gt;Bloomberg View&lt;/a&gt;, which
runs just over a minute and distills the essence of a longer (usually
well thought-out) op-ed. (I guess by this logic the ideal podcast would
be 0 seconds - very Cagean.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it seems like the Berg is phasing this one out. It no longer appears
on the website or on most podcast providers, and the RSS feed I had
(from iTunes) on &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.bambuna.podcastaddict&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34;&gt;Podcast
Addict&lt;/a&gt;
(a truly excellent app) suddenly returned
&lt;code&gt;SSLHandshakeException: java.security.cert.CertPathValidatorException: Trust anchor for certification path not found&lt;/code&gt;.
I emailed the developer and he promptly (shout-out Xavier! He really is
awesome) explained that SSL cert verification in modern versions of
Android is done by the device for all apps (except web browsers), so
this error is not coming from inside the app. I confirmed that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t
accidentally disabled my trust of any previously accepted certificate,
and he later showed me that the SSL cert for the RSS feed was indeed
expired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I emailed Bloomberg about this, but I think they are sunsetting this
podcast, and their support ticket confirmation email never showed up. In
the meantime I wanted to just grab those episodes, so I did it old
school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;import requests
import xml.etree.ElementTree as ET

feed = requests.get(&#39;https://feeds.bloomberg.fm/BLM8578726790&#39;, verify=False).text
# you need to disable verify because of the dodgy SSL. requests throws up a warning telling you that this is very foolish
feed = ET.fromstring(feed)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After fooling around with the &lt;code&gt;xml&lt;/code&gt; I get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;for child in feed.getchildren()[0].getchildren():
    if child.tag == &#39;item&#39;:
        x = child.getchildren()
        print(x[0].text)
        print(x[-2].text)

&amp;gt;
Bloomberg Opinion Radio: Weekend Edition for 7-12-19 (Podcast)
https://assets.bwbx.io/av/users/iqjWHBFdfxIU/vrsTK.0wJcuQ/v4.mp3
How to Tame Europe’s Game of Thrones: Editorial (Podcast)
https://assets.bwbx.io/av/users/iqjWHBFdfxIU/vRijgKsrekSc/v4.mp3
Ramesh Ponnuru on the Obamacare Lawsuit Paradox (Podcast)
https://assets.bwbx.io/av/users/iqjWHBFdfxIU/vRzEW1v7.DEc/v4.mp3
Demanding Straight Answers on Immigration: Editorial (Podcast)
https://assets.bwbx.io/av/users/iqjWHBFdfxIU/viPbxsujOdcQ/v4.mp3

etc..
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I just grabbed the ones I wanted with &lt;code&gt;wget&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir podcasts &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd podcasts/
wget -O pelosi.mp3 https://assets.bwbx.io/av/users/iqjWHBFdfxIU/vAThJHLXwFKM/v4.mp3

etc...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sent them to my phone with Bluetooth, and added the &lt;code&gt;bluetooth&lt;/code&gt; folder
as a virtual podcast. And there you go, podcasts the old fashioned way!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Truth Is Whatever We Believe</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/truth/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/truth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You could tell a story in which the West is in decline, and China (and
perhaps India, Africa, whoever) is rising to take its place. Similarly,
you could take the post Cold War view that liberalism survives all
attacks, and that the current backlash against liberalism will also run
out of steam. Which of these is correct? Maybe whichever we believe it
is. I thought of this while reading Jack Weatherford&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Genghis Khan and
the Making of the Modern World&lt;/em&gt;. He talks about Kublai Khan&amp;rsquo;s conquest
of China, and his assiduous use of propaganda. While the Mongols fought
the Song in Southern China and tried to unite the country, they were
able to change their public perception from that of foreign invaders to
be cast out, to that of new rulers, graced by heaven, who gained
legitimacy with every new victory. Many people defected to them and were
treated fairly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the leaders of all the great powers today suspect that their
narratives might not be true, and that destiny might not actually carry
them forward. But they hope it to be the case, and try to convince
others. Perhaps that is all that is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Futility of Writing</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/futility_of_writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/futility_of_writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Haven&amp;rsquo;t written anything in a while, and so this post seems appropriate.
It seems sometimes like in the Internet age, everything has been said,
and it&amp;rsquo;s mostly wrong. Take any news event in the last 24 hours, and you
will find on Twitter a vast panoply of opinions, taking every possible
perspective: joking, chiding, worrying, connecting it to the Grain Riots
of 1874. These will link to longer takes, rushing up like mushrooms
before the internet&amp;rsquo;s atttention shifts and we forget all about it. I
tend to be cynical, but my cynicism is in every case pre-empted: and so
is any other position I might take. Considering how I might want to
respond, I&amp;rsquo;m confronted with the feeling that I won&amp;rsquo;t be adding
anything, and so I usually refrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Of making many books there is no end&lt;/em&gt;, says Ecclesiastes. Today
everyone can publish everything and distribute everything they have to
say. In some ways this is good - more variety in media. It may have hurt
society in some ways, because when you remove all gatekeepers you give
equal weight to every crank and paranoiac. But it has also caused me to
doubt my interest in and love for the printed word. Lately I find myself
reading more maths, which for all its troubles, is a much calmer place
to be. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s a long term solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conversation</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/conversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/conversation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I like to think that I&amp;rsquo;ve taught myself to become a better
conversationalist. I know that makes me sounds rather dull; but I do try
not to think about it as a set of procedures or an algorithm, but rather
as a general attitude that can make you more fun to hang out with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Famously, the golden rule of conversation is to &amp;ldquo;ask people about
themselves and let them talk&amp;rdquo;. This is true; with the caveat that &lt;strong&gt;you
need to be interested in their answers&lt;/strong&gt;. This means, essentially, that
you need to cultivate an interest in all sorts of people, to open
yourself up to conversations outside your immediate areas of interest.
If you can&amp;rsquo;t make yourself care about someone else&amp;rsquo;s life, they&amp;rsquo;ll be
aware of it. Luckily, people are fascinating - if you can&amp;rsquo;t see that,
read some fiction!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open-ended or ambiguous questions, of course, are infinitely better.
&amp;ldquo;What is your favourite part of &amp;ndash;&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Do you think that &amp;ndash;&amp;rdquo; are better
than questions with specific answers (&amp;ldquo;do you like it?&amp;quot;), and &amp;ldquo;what do
you do?&amp;rdquo; is better than &amp;ldquo;what line of work are you in?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common idea is that you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t ask boring questions such as
&amp;ldquo;where are you from&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;what job do you do&amp;rdquo;. I don&amp;rsquo;t agree with this
bit of wisdom. To me, hitting someone you&amp;rsquo;ve just met with something
like &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rsquo;s the scariest thing you&amp;rsquo;ve ever done?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;are humans
becoming obsolete?&amp;rdquo; is somewhat obnoxious. It&amp;rsquo;s a way of putting
yourself in the centre, marking yourself as a Bold and Interesting
Person who has no time for little minds. Some people find small talk
reassuring, at least at the beginning, and there&amp;rsquo;s a reason why it&amp;rsquo;s a
pretty common social lubricant. To me the goal of conversation is to
find the other person&amp;rsquo;s comfort zone and interests, find what excites
them, find some way that it intersects with your own interests, and
build on that. Everyone is different: some people like to talk about
hypotheticals, some people like talking about their jobs, some like
debating current events, some like emotional discussions, and some
people don&amp;rsquo;t like to talk at all, or don&amp;rsquo;t want to talk to you, and
shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be pushed. A non-threatening opener is your gambit into
finding which one it is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhetoric &amp; Rationalism</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/rhetoric_rationalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/rhetoric_rationalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s common to think of rhetoric as a gloss on top of &amp;lsquo;true&amp;rsquo; thinking,
mere packaging for the intellectual content of our ideas. From some of
the Platonic dialogues it seems like rhetoric, (or &lt;em&gt;sophistry&lt;/em&gt;, which
Plato made into an insult) is a foil to rational thought, an alternative
tradition which privileges aesthetic value - elegance of expression -
over content. (I seem to remember hearing a podcast [probably &lt;a href=&#34;https://partiallyexaminedlife.com/2013/05/14/ep76-deleuze/&#34;&gt;this
one&lt;/a&gt;] about
how Deleuze and Guattari suggest that as a better criterion than Occam&amp;rsquo;s
Razor for choosing a scientific explanation.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his book &lt;em&gt;Amusing Ourselves to Death&lt;/em&gt; Neil Postman mentions this as a
possible difference between the media of oral and written culture: when
things are said, they must be constructed to be beautiful; when written,
people care more about how much sense they make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be a similar idea with &lt;em&gt;mishna&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;gemara&lt;/em&gt;: could this be
why the &lt;em&gt;gemara&lt;/em&gt; so often reinterprets a pithy &lt;em&gt;mishna&lt;/em&gt; to a clunky but
more consistent reading?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course the underlying, mischievous idea that one is not
necessarily better - they are just different forms of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallel Texts</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/parallel_texts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/parallel_texts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An anecdote from Richard Rhodes&#39; book &lt;em&gt;The Making of the Atomic Bomb&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of curiosity in 1940, while visiting Berkeley to deliver a
lecture, Enrico Fermi attended a seminar one of [J. Robert]
Oppenheimer&amp;rsquo;s protégés led in the master&amp;rsquo;s style. &amp;ldquo;Emilio,&amp;rdquo; Fermi
joked afterward with Segrè, &amp;ldquo;I am getting rusty and old. I cannot
follow the highbrow theory developed by Oppenheimer&amp;rsquo;s pupils anymore.
I went to their seminar and was depressed by my inability to
understand them. Only the last sentence cheered me up; it was: &amp;lsquo;and
this is Fermi&amp;rsquo;s theory of beta decay.&#39;&amp;rdquo; (p. 667)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with Menachot 29b, you&amp;rsquo;ll see the parallel
immediately. In case you don&amp;rsquo;t, I quote it here (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sefaria.org.il/Menachot.29b.4?lang=bi&amp;amp;with=all&amp;amp;lang2=en&#34;&gt;via
Sefaria&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moses said before God: Master of the Universe, show him to me. God
said to him: Return behind you. Moses went and sat at the end of the
eighth row in Rabbi Akiva&amp;rsquo;s study hall and did not understand what
they were saying. Moses&amp;rsquo; strength waned, as he thought his Torah
knowledge was deficient. When Rabbi Akiva arrived at the discussion of
one matter, his students said to him: My teacher, from where do you
derive this? Rabbi Akiva said to them: It is a &lt;em&gt;halakha&lt;/em&gt; transmitted
to Moses from Sinai. When Moses heard this, his mind was put at ease,
as this too was part of the Torah that he was to receive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Depressing Art // Likable Politicians</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/depressing_art_likable_politicians/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/depressing_art_likable_politicians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are elections now, and people here are deeply cynical about the
slate of candidates. Political despair is the dominant tone, and has
been for some time. This is also true in the wider world, where few
politicians inspire trust or excitement. There was talk this week of
Elizabeth Warren launching a Presidential campaign, which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/i-dont-hate-women-candidates-i-just-hated-hillary-and-coincidentally-im-starting-to-hate-elizabeth-warren&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;I Don&amp;rsquo;t
Hate Women Candidates &amp;mdash; I Just Hated Hillary and Coincidentally I&amp;rsquo;m
Starting to Hate Elizabeth
Warren&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;
references. I don&amp;rsquo;t really have an opinion on Warren, but it made me
think of a politician I do find powerfully likable: Alexandria
Ocasio-Cortez. Trying to put my finger on what it was, I came up with 1)
cheerfulness and 2) optimism. O-C is a politician, and invariably does
need to say divisive things and spar with rivals; but she seems excited,
spontaneous, and again, optimistic. That optimism is very valuable in
such a toxic political climate. Perhaps Obama as a Senator projected a
similar fresh optimism. It probably is made easier when a young
candidate puts together a string of victories. Beto O&amp;rsquo;Rouke&amp;rsquo;s defeat to
Ted Cruz - no matter how predictable - may have detracted slightly from
his likability. (And for a bit of nonpartisanship, I&amp;rsquo;d mention Ben
Shapiro as a conservative whose precociousness and Reaganesque moral
optimism has won him a lot of attention, though he&amp;rsquo;s not exactly a
political figure - more in the &amp;ldquo;discourse&amp;rdquo; game.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should stress that I do not think this likability necessarily
translates to leadership ability or worthwhile ideas. This approbation
is from a rhetoric/political communication point of view. &amp;ldquo;Cheer&amp;rdquo; and
&amp;ldquo;optimism&amp;rdquo; are hard to fake successfully: the public is used to seeing
politicians try all the time. When they exist sincerely, they are
valuable assets, but not a substitute for good policy and governance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the music I like is not exactly fun. A fair amount of it might
be described as something one might bump themselves off to. And yet I
don&amp;rsquo;t really relate to it from a depressed space. In a way, I find it
cathartic to listen to other people&amp;rsquo;s depression (and perhaps feel
better by comparison!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an old debate about if some artists need to suffer from
depression, or other mental illness, to be successful at their craft.
Many find this idea repugnant, with its implication that these people
must live in a state of untreated illness in order to ply their trade. I
certainly don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone&amp;rsquo;s mental health should take second place to
their artistic output. We as a society should do everything possible to
make professional medical help available to everyone, and encourage
people to make use of it. But it is at least possible that there are
artistic truths that are accessible only to those deep in the well of
melancholy. Better, certainly, that we lived without these truths, and
still had Elliot Smith. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t alter the fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Depressive_realism&#34;&gt;depressive
realism&lt;/a&gt; dovetails
with this nicely: if we imagine that the world is fundamentally a tragic
place, and that neurotypical people deal with it via defensive mental
obfuscating, it might make sense that we would be drawn to the work of
the depressed, seeing in the expression of these unlucky prophets a
vision of a truth almost, but not quite perceived.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prayer</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/prayer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/prayer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in my yeshiva days, I struggled with the concept of prayer. We
observe that sometimes people pray for things and aren&amp;rsquo;t answered -
after all, we all pray every day for health, wealth and the ultimate
redemption. So the underlying theory seems to be something along the
lines of prayer increasing your odds. Or, since presumably these things
are deterministic, your score: perhaps a young, healthy person needs 100
points to recover from an illness, and has 80 points on their own merit,
prayer can boost them 20 points and make it happen. Perhaps to recover
from a rare cancer requires 10,000 points and so even a pretty righteous
person, with many people praying for them, might get like, 8,000 points,
close but no cigar. (Perhaps this even warrants them a temporary
remission, but not a full one.)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
But all of this seems a little silly: the &amp;ldquo;vending machine&amp;rdquo; model of
divine worship. Insert prayers, get rewarded. In fact there are Jewish
sources that claim that God makes life especially tough for the
righteous because he desires their prayers. A model that appeals to me
more would be the exact opposite: that prayer affects nothing at all,
but is a form of meditation and Divine closeness, and so is worthy for
its own sake. But in this case praying for something to happen does
absolutely nothing, which makes the activity seem somewhat paradoxical.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Of course, at its core this is entangled with the problem of theodicy,
so it&amp;rsquo;s no wonder that it&amp;rsquo;s such a conundrum.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Male Feminist? // Stats and the Social Sciences</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/what_is_a_male_feminist_stats_and_the_social_sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/what_is_a_male_feminist_stats_and_the_social_sciences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, a lot of people were sharing an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WJvm5-lO_Dw&#34;&gt;Aziz Ansari
bit&lt;/a&gt; about feminism. The
thrust - if you don&amp;rsquo;t want to click through - is that if you think men
and women deserve equal treatment, then you are a feminist, and
shouldn&amp;rsquo;t try avoid the label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a good joke, but philosophically I think it is a little bit more
complex. Words have multiple shades of meaning, and words with far less
complex histories can be hard to define simply. Put simply, what is
feminism? It can mean a wide range of views, from &amp;lsquo;Wages for Housework&amp;rsquo;
to &amp;lsquo;Lean In&amp;rsquo; neoliberal feminism to intersectionality to TERFs to
arguments about abortion and the wage gap. If someone feels that women
deserve to earn equally to men, but that the wage gap is explained by
revealed preferences, unequal choices of hours and profession, is he not
a feminist? If a Christian believes abortion is murder, is she not a
feminist?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is undoubtedly complexity here, and I&amp;rsquo;m here to say this: &lt;em&gt;I think
men should not be involved in this discussion&lt;/em&gt;. It is women who are
affected by these issues, and they who should decide what feminism is
defined by, each in her own way. I think this is a reasonable claim,
though not a common one, even if one does not subscribe to the
identitarian &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standpoint_theory&#34;&gt;standpoint
theory&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; epistemology
that claims the impossibility of outsider knowledge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a corollary of this is, since I can&amp;rsquo;t define feminism, I prefer to
call myself &lt;em&gt;pro-feminist&lt;/em&gt;, not a &lt;em&gt;feminist&lt;/em&gt;. It is up to women to
decide what feminism is. But I can&amp;rsquo;t call myself something I can&amp;rsquo;t
define.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put another way: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what feminism is, but whatever it is,
I&amp;rsquo;m for it&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Science may be a sexy term for statistics, but statistics is more
sexy than it&amp;rsquo;s given credit for. Any social science, under the Popperian
paradigm, must make predictions: diagnosing a structure means nothing if
it has no predictive capacity. (Or else it&amp;rsquo;s humanities, kind of the way
some historians want to go, and the way psychoanalysis has gone
completely). Are, say, political scientists any better than monkeys
throwing darts? That&amp;rsquo;s why they need statistics. So both data science
and all of the social sciences can be defined as &lt;em&gt;applied statistics&lt;/em&gt;
(with the balance just varying between domain knowledge vs stats
knowledge, though any long-term DS project does involve getting deep
into the domain knowledge). Where it gets weird is where DS models and
makes predictions without an explanatory model, such as the case of NLP.
Statistical relationships working by themselves, not being supported by
any deep idea of how things fundamentally are supposed to work. The next
word is &amp;ldquo;meeting&amp;rdquo;, that green lump is a tree, just based on probability.
This was the subject of a debate between Google&amp;rsquo;s Peter Norvig and Noam
Chomsky, the former sums it up in a fascinating, deep-ranging blog post
&lt;a href=&#34;http://norvig.com/chomsky.html&#34;&gt;over here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Justice Warriors on the Intellectual Dark Web // Who Needs the News? // The Nature of Reality</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/social_justice_warriors_on_the_intellectual_dark_web_who_needs_the_news_the_nature_of_reality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/social_justice_warriors_on_the_intellectual_dark_web_who_needs_the_news_the_nature_of_reality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A very overdiscussed topic lately is political correctness, and if
there&amp;rsquo;s too much of it. I propose the following three points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least some measure of socially ordained political correctness is
unquestionably a good thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a point where social monitoring of offensive speech becomes
intrusive, burdensome and overall not worthwhile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;lsquo;PC Culture&amp;rsquo; is currently unevenly distributed - there are some
places which have it in very high levels (many university campuses,
say), whereas there are also plenty of places where some pretty
offensive things are considered acceptable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically my feeling is that there is a high level of variance among
people. Outside of the Western world there is a wild thicket of systems
of etiquette, views on race and caste and culture and gender, etc. And
even within the West, there is quite a lot of variance. I think this
variance is OK, a part of human nature. What the internet has changed is
that we see much more of each other&amp;rsquo;s views, and have more opportunity
to take offence, such that people get angrier and more polarised. The
internet is less like a global village than like all the villages in the
world compressed into one physical space, haphazardly glimpsing each
other&amp;rsquo;s business and getting offended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also suspect that a lot of people within places that have high levels
of PC aren&amp;rsquo;t fully on board with the culture, but don&amp;rsquo;t feel it&amp;rsquo;s worth
taking on. I strongly endorse this hypothetical view, because a) this
doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like the biggest deal, and b) people&amp;rsquo;s will probably
regress back to a calmer mean over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the late, revered programmer Aaron Swartz, patron saint of the
Internet, has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/hatethenews&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; I
categorically disagree with. Swartz argues that reading the news is
pointless because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t affect your life, and that it is a form of
mindless entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By that logic, should you read news of scientific developments? It
affects your life very little, too, and it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely that someone
outside of a very specialised field will be able to contribute. Why read
anything besides technical literature from your profession, and perhaps
investment advice? If one is going to read anything, it might as well be
keeping up with the world around you, and one might even be able to use
it to make small talk with other human beings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also think that this argument stems from a time when the media seemed
sturdier. Nowadays, the media business model is barely alive, and the
media&amp;rsquo;s role in a democracy doesn&amp;rsquo;t just work on its own. Swartz argues
that if the newspaper criticises the mayor, the mayor will apologise or
justify herself or whatever, so why does the reader need to get
involved? But nowadays the mayor has her own media. You could still
argue, as Swartz does, that one individual&amp;rsquo;s opinion, or their vote,
doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter. But one might say in today&amp;rsquo;s terms that that
argument &amp;ldquo;doesn&amp;rsquo;t scale&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;English speakers encountering the words for scientific things in other
languages often find them somewhat childlike, but that&amp;rsquo;s only because
English obfuscates them with Latin and Greek, because tradition. Just
one example: TV in German is Fernsehen, &amp;ldquo;see-far&amp;rdquo;; in English it&amp;rsquo;s the
same, but a hideous Greek-Latin hybrid. Leaving aside the Sapir-Whorff
hypothesis, it&amp;rsquo;s beyond a doubt that the solidity of our language hides
an enormous amount of uncertainty. Not to get too Kantian, but in a
sense scientific models - not just of black holes and quantum particles,
but of all matter, consciousness, life! - are weird, hacky concepts,
leaky metaphors which partially describe observations of phenomena that
multiple people experience. I found this idea of the ubiquity and
fundamental nature of metaphor in human experience in a book I&amp;rsquo;m reading
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Origin-Consciousness-Breakdown-Bicameral-Mind/dp/0618057072&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Origin of Consciousness in the Breakdown of the Bicameral
Mind&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;),
and I&amp;rsquo;ll quote from it somewhat at length.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A random glance at the etymologies of common words in a dictionary
will demonstrate [the ubiquity of metaphors]. Or take the naming of
various fauna and flora in their Latin indicants, or even in their
wonderful common English names, such as stag beetle, lady&amp;rsquo;s-slipper,
darning needle, Queen Anne&amp;rsquo;s lace, or buttercup. The human body is a
particularly generative metaphier [his term for a source of
metaphors], creating previously unspeakable distinctions in a throng
of areas. The &lt;em&gt;head&lt;/em&gt; of an army, table, page, bed, ship, household, or
nail, or of steam or water; the &lt;em&gt;face&lt;/em&gt; of a clock, cliff, card, or
crystal; the &lt;em&gt;eyes&lt;/em&gt; of needles, winds, storms, targets, flowers, or
potatoes; the &lt;em&gt;brow&lt;/em&gt; of a hill; the &lt;em&gt;cheeks&lt;/em&gt; of a vise; the &lt;em&gt;teeth&lt;/em&gt; of
cogs or combs; the &lt;em&gt;lips&lt;/em&gt; of pitchers, craters, augers; the &lt;em&gt;tongues&lt;/em&gt;
of shoes, board joints, or railway switches; the &lt;em&gt;arm&lt;/em&gt; of a chair or
the sea; the &lt;em&gt;leg&lt;/em&gt; of a table, compass, sailor&amp;rsquo;s voyage, or cricket
field; and so on and on. Or the &lt;em&gt;foot&lt;/em&gt; of this page. Or the &lt;em&gt;leaf&lt;/em&gt; you
will soon turn. All of these concrete metaphors increase enormously
our powers of perception of the world about us and our understanding
of it, and literally create new objects. Indeed, language is an organ
of perception, not simply a means of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;This is indeed the nub (knob), heart, pith, kernel, core, marrow,
etc. of my argument, which itself is a metaphor and &amp;lsquo;seen&amp;rsquo; only with
the mind&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;eye&amp;rsquo;. In the abstractions of human relations, the skin
becomes a particularly important metaphier. We get or stay &amp;lsquo;in touch&amp;rsquo;
with others who may be &amp;lsquo;thick-&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;thin-skinned&amp;rsquo; or perhaps &amp;lsquo;touchy&amp;rsquo;
in which case they have to be &amp;lsquo;handled&amp;rsquo; carefully lest we &amp;lsquo;rub&amp;rsquo; them
the wrong way; we may have a &amp;lsquo;feeling&amp;rsquo; for another person with whom we
may have a &amp;lsquo;touching&amp;rsquo; experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concepts of science are all of this kind, abstract concepts
generated by concrete metaphors. In physics, we have force,
acceleration (to increase one&amp;rsquo;s steps), inertia (originally an
indolent person), impedance, resistance, fields, and now charm. In
physiology, the metaphier of a machine has been at the very center of
discovery. We understand the brain by metaphors to everything from
batteries and telegraphy to computers and holograms. Medical practice
is sometimes dictated by metaphor. In the eighteenth century, the
heart in fever was like a boiling pot, and so bloodletting was
prescribed to reduce its fuel. And even today, a great deal of
medicine is based upon the military metaphor of defense of the body
against attacks of this or that. The very concept of law in Greek
derives from &lt;em&gt;nomos,&lt;/em&gt; the word for the foundations of a building. To
be liable, or bound in law, comes from the Latin &lt;em&gt;ligare,&lt;/em&gt; meaning to
bind with cord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early times, language and its referents climbed up from the
concrete to the abstract on the steps of metaphors, even, we may say,
created the abstract on the bases of metaphors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not always obvious that metaphor has played this all important
function. But this is because the concrete metaphiers become hidden in
phonemic change, leaving the words to exist on their own. Even such an
unmetaphorical-sounding word as the verb &amp;lsquo;to be&amp;rsquo; was generated from a
metaphor. It comes from the Sanskrit &lt;em&gt;bhu&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;to grow, or make grow,&amp;rdquo;
while the English forms &amp;lsquo;am&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;is&amp;rsquo; have evolved from the same root
as the Sanskrit &lt;em&gt;asmi,&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ldquo;to breathe.&amp;rdquo; It is something of a lovely
surprise that the irregular conjugation of our most nondescript verb
is thus a record of a time when man had no independent word for
&amp;lsquo;existence&amp;rsquo; and could only say that something &amp;lsquo;grows&amp;rsquo; or that it
&amp;ldquo;breathes.&amp;rdquo; Of course we are not conscious that the concept of being
is thus generated from a metaphor about growing and breathing.
Abstract words are ancient coins whose concrete images in the busy
give-and-take of talk have worn away with use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because in our brief lives we catch so little of the vastnesses of
history, we tend too much to think of language as being solid as a
dictionary, with a granite-like permanence, rather than as the rampant
restless sea of metaphor which it is. Indeed, if we consider the
changes in vocabulary that have occurred over the last few millennia,
and project them several millennia hence, an interesting paradox
arises. For if we ever achieve a language that has the power of
expressing everything, then metaphor will no longer be possible. I
would not say, in that case, my love is like a red, red rose, for love
would have exploded into terms for its thousands of nuances, and
applying the correct term would leave the rose metaphorically dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democracy &amp; Elitism // Fish</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/democracy___elitism_fish/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/democracy___elitism_fish/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;salon&amp;rdquo; here where people get together once in a fortnight to
discuss a topic. The other week we were talking about politics and I
floated the idea that there are &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;rdquo; voters: those who
understand the issues to a greater extent and vote correctly
representing their interests, and those who understand less, whose vote
is essentially adding noise to the system. I&amp;rsquo;ve been groping towards an
idea of &amp;ldquo;democratic elitism&amp;rdquo; for a while, in which the great value of
democracy, I think, is that everyone&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;interests&lt;/em&gt; are represented
equally, but the messy practice of democracy muddies that and leads to
suboptimal outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this as in most things, it turns out that there&amp;rsquo;s a literature. While
reading Alan Ryan&amp;rsquo;s biography &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/John-Dewey-High-American-Liberalism/dp/1511384352&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;John Dewey and the High Tide of American
Liberalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
I came across Dewey&amp;rsquo;s debates with journalist Walter Lippmann, a
towering figure in American journalism I&amp;rsquo;d never heard of. He studied
under Santayana at Harvard, co-founded the &lt;em&gt;New Republic&lt;/em&gt;, and was a
much read journalist and critic for half a century. (This &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.foreignaffairs.com/reviews/review-essay/2015-02-11/walter-lippmann-and-american-century&#34;&gt;helpful 1980
retrospective&lt;/a&gt;
in &lt;em&gt;Foreign Affairs&lt;/em&gt; is temporarily ungated, probably due to an
oversight.) In the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Journalism#Writing_for_experts_or_for_ordinary_citizens?&#34;&gt;Lippmann-Dewey&lt;/a&gt;
debates, Lippmann made several very prescient critiques of the
media-public pipeline: firstly, reality is too complicated for anyone to
understand, and journalists tend to fall back on a stereotype backed up
by some reporting. Secondly, the public has little interest in political
engagement, and is not prepared to pay the price of thorough,
well-researched journalism. &amp;ldquo;For a dollar, you may not even get an
armful of candy, but for a dollar or less people expect
reality/representations of truth to fall into their laps.&amp;rdquo; A lot of
important facts are impossible to find out, and editorial judgment adds
bias to the allocation of news coverage. Thus, people don&amp;rsquo;t want to keep
up, and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to even if they could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lippmann advocated a technocracy, where a governing elite would be
advised by a cadre of technocrats, experts in a very narrow field.
(Lippmann&amp;rsquo;s name is thus associated with our modern vision of the
neoliberal state, and in fact it was Foucault who pointed out that the
the term originated at the first meeting in Paris of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colloque_Walter_Lippmann&#34;&gt;Colloque
Walter
Lippmann&lt;/a&gt;.)
Dewey&amp;rsquo;s side of the argument was in favour of civilian journalism, and a
&amp;ldquo;Great Society&amp;rdquo; of slow community-wide consensus. (Always majestic in
idealism but obscurely phrased, Dewey&amp;rsquo;s writing was perfectly described
by Oliver Wendell Homes Jr.:&amp;ldquo;So methought God would have spoken had He
been inarticulate but keenly desirous to tell you how it was.&amp;quot;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan notes that the classic theorist of democratic elitism is actually
Joseph Schumpeter. In his famous work &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capitalism,_Socialism_and_Democracy&#34;&gt;Capitalism, Socialism and
Democracy&lt;/a&gt;
Schumpeter argued that a) the people are unlikely to know what is best
for them, since they are usually manipulated by politicians, and b) even
if they did have a clear agenda, they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know the best means to
achieving it. He thus (following Weber) argued for a largely arms-length
democratic system, in which policy decisions are made at a government
level and the public&amp;rsquo;s role is restricted to choosing one of these
options and giving it a rubber stamp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the issue here, where a lot of people disagree with me, is if
there really is a rational, ideal way to run a modern society. The
democratic upheaval of the last few years (which no doubt sowed the seed
of these musings) can arguably be attributed to the failure of the
watchman state during the financial crisis and America&amp;rsquo;s war on terror.
If the technocrats cannot claim greater knowledge than the public, what
authority do they hold? And if reason has no special status in public
life, does that mean that we are all forever doomed to shout at each
other to no end, ignorant voters on a darkling plain?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, for the first time in my life, I picked up a whole fish (red
tilapia) at the souk, and decided to cook it. It feels so strange and
primitive! I gingerly unwrapped the newspaper and plastic bag, let the
liquid (blood?) drain, marinated it, added some garlic and thyme and
banged it in the oven. A brave new world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biodiversity // Doctors // BMX</title>
      <link>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/biodiversity_doctors_bmx/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://lordgrenville.github.io/posts/biodiversity_doctors_bmx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been working at home this week, and leaving the windows open, as I like doing in all but the hottest weather. But I&amp;rsquo;ve been bothered by these guys on the right. &lt;label for=&#34;marginnote-1efa3ae6e2edb8b9846c9f2f1f3c3eed-0&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;&gt;⊕&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;marginnote-1efa3ae6e2edb8b9846c9f2f1f3c3eed-0&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34;/&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://lordgrenville.github.io/img/Aedes_Albopictus.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Aedes Albopictus (public domain image via the Centre for Disease Control)&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Googling mosquitoes with zebra-striped abdomens reveals that this is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aedes_albopictus&#34;&gt;tiger mosquito&lt;/a&gt;, an aggressive invader from SE Asia. Ranked as one of the hundred worst invasive species, it originally spread on packing crates and has penetrated most of the world, first being seen in Israel in 2003. And besides for worse things, such as being disease vectors, they are unusually awful pests: they hunt by day, unlike regular mozzies, and can easily adapt to living in almost any human habitat, not needing a humid bog. I can testify to their peculiarly aggressive nature, not minding being brushed away or swatted at, persisting until finding blood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the side-effects of globalisation is the cross-pollination of nonhuman species all over the world, and simple Darwinism makes it likely that the strongest contenders from foreign environments will quickly take over many others (note the invasive Indian Mynahs and crows so prevalent here). It seems inevitable that this will result in a significant reduction in biodiversity. (The WWF claimed &lt;a href=&#34;https://qz.com/1443473/wwf-living-planet-report-says-humans-wiped-out-60-of-animals-since-1970/&#34;&gt;in a report this week&lt;/a&gt; that 60% of species had been wiped out since 1970.) This seems unpreventable, hard to track, and there might even be some unanticipated positive consequences. But it is a remarkable phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor recommended I have a mole taken out, so I went to a plastic surgeon, who said it was unnecessary, but he could do it anyway. &amp;ldquo;OK,&amp;rdquo; I said. &amp;ldquo;OK what?&amp;rdquo; he asked, with typical Israeli patience. &amp;ldquo;Well, you say no, she says yes - how can I know what to do?&amp;rdquo; He waved his hand. &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about it, you can rely on me. It&amp;rsquo;s the easiest thing to prescribe an op. That&amp;rsquo;s not called being a doctor! Anyone could say that. It takes knowledge to say, it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary.&amp;rdquo; It reminded me a bit of doctrine of &lt;a href=&#34;https://he.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D7%9B%D7%95%D7%97_%D7%93%D7%94%D7%99%D7%AA%D7%A8%D7%90_%D7%A2%D7%93%D7%99%D7%A3&#34;&gt;כוחא דהיתרא עדיף&lt;/a&gt; (Beitza 2b) - anyone can prohibit something, but it takes a scholar to permit it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the way back from the doctor I walked past BMXers doing tricks outside the Cinematheque. What they do is unreal, Matrix stuff; it seems to override the law of gravity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

